hello and welcome this is active
inference org stream 6.1 it's January
22nd
2024 and we're here with the D20
governance team and project so I will
let them all introduce themselves this
should be a very fun and interactive
session so thank you all for joining and
looking forward to your presentation and
the disc
discussion cool yeah thank you Daniel um
so I'm sent uh hoston uh and I am a
community lead at The Meta governance
project and uh one of the developers and
researchers with the D20 governance
project um I'm here with Asel andita um
and I'll let them introduce themselves
now maybe uh Hazel and then
[Music]
hi um thank you for coming to the live
stream uh my name is Hazel I'm
Affiliated I'm kind of in the mdo of
community environment atmosphere um I am
political theorist I'm a researcher with
D20 um before I pass to Janita also want
to highlight another of our team member
who isn't here V is her birthday happy
birthday
V hi I'm Janita I'm a software developer
um have been involved in the Dow
ecosystem working on some projects um
around uh dowas in the past and uh this
project is my main um sort of uh
interaction with the metago community
but um I'm generally pretty interested
in in all the work that they're doing
and um yeah researcher and governance
Etc
cool um so with that we're planning to
do a uh presentation today and then the
presentation will also have some
interactive demos uh for people who are
joining us in the Stream um and yeah so
with that we'll get started um I should
also say before we get started that um I
want to thank Daniel for inviting us to
come and speak at this um I've known
Daniel
for as long as I've been doing the
community lead work at medov and I've
had a lot of uh really interesting
discussions uh with him about uh uh
cognitive security uh stigma G um and
governance in general um un less uh
familiar with the kind of uh resources
is happening at the Active inference
Institute um so really glad that uh
Daniel and the their Community was
interested in having us come and join so
that we can um present our work and
learn from the insights of this group of
researchers so with that um let's go
ahead and get into the
presentation um great so uh before
starting um there is this uh Discord
link and actually um it's not in my
clipboard so I'm going to generate a uh
going to generate a new invite um and
then I'll will share it in our chat here
in Zoom then Daniel can share it
um in any like whatever way is
applicable um and then yeah so this is
going to be a uh link to our Discord
server um where the bot for this project
is hosted um it's the D20 governance
server um and we're going to do some
demos today and so if you want to
participate this is the place to join
for that um if you join uh come in and
say hi um and uh yeah so with that um
I'm going to pass it over to Hazel who's
going to give us a bit of an overview
for today's presentation yeah um so the
flow of this presentation today will be
um some demonstration of the
functionalities we built sprinkled with
um some conceptual thinking um so we're
going to start with giving you guys a
background on where this how this
project came to be and we will introduce
our first functionality um that's D20 AG
where we're going to be interacting and
we will demo the culture modules and
talk a little bit about Community rule
which is where and how this was inspir
this project and we'll talk about two
more functionalities that's value group
voice actually three more and continuous
input and then we'll end with um a Q&A
and
discussion so moving on to the next
slide um a really brief overview of this
project is D20 is a Discord bot that
allows communities to play governance
games in an AI large language model
mediated environment so groups of people
can come together to embark on a
governance what we call governance
quests and experience a diversity of
governance structures decision-making
processes power distributions and
cultural Dynamics um through building
the discore bot D20 aims to help lay the
collective decision-making foundations
necessary for online communities to
conduct their own governance experiments
do governance education do future
scenario planning and make real life
decisions while bonding communities
through play and a sense of
playfulness
I'll pass it to
chanita yeah um so actually sent if you
don't mind going to the next slide I
think there's a a little
gift I wanted to
reference um okay so the original
inspiration for this project was a tool
called Community rule which um this gift
on the screen depicts Community rule is
basically
a templating tool that allows you to
define a modu structure for your
community's
governance so there are four types of um
modules that you may select and combine
culture modules decision modules process
modules and structure modules and uh
Community rule basically allows you
to um combine and create sort of nested
hierarchies of these modules that you
can then export into a template format
um so our original Vision was to
basically take this allow someone to
export this template and then import it
into our Discord bot and have it just
work for um sort of uh your community's
governance
um but we also at the same time wanted
to um kind of have this
like uh notion of game play or um allow
people to experiment with these modules
in a like very low stakes manner that
you could then um you know move forward
and and um uh take into higher Stakes
situations like actually using these
modules to govern your community so um
the idea of low stakes is kind of where
the governance game idea came from um so
we started out uh you know developing
um a more fully-fledged kind of game
experience and we were trying to um
design a a narrative that took people
through a series of different uh
decisions that they had to make as a
community um and and we're trying to be
uh pretty um honest to the original like
structure of community role with respect
to these four different types of modules
um but some something we realized as we
went along was that like game game
design and like making a
really kind of interesting and exciting
gameplay experience is like a a hard
problem in and of itself um and we were
kind of trying to accomplish a lot of
things at once we realized so we decided
to pair back um the game structure a bit
and and sort of focus it around what we
call like these mini quests or
governance
experiences um where um people in the
community can kind of um like still
experiment but in a in a sort of like on
a shorter time frame and with less
narrative overhead um they can still
experiment with uh these governance
modules um so we'll we'll get a bit more
specific about the actual structure of
the game later on but that was kind of
the origin story of the D20 bot um one
other thing I'll mention is that um as
we were like developing this and um
doing play tests with different
communities um
we got a lot of feedback around the sort
of um this llm mediated communication
feature so one of our original ideas was
to um Implement these like implement the
idea of culture models but in a more
whacky manner by um using llms to
modulate um how people are
communicating um so you know for example
we have like an eloquence con types in
the Discord is uh trans translated into
Shakespearean English um and we found
that like people were finding a lot of
delight in these culture modules and so
we started thinking more about um you
know how this game can allow allow
people to experiment with um
communication and an llm mediated
information landscape or like how um
even the frustration that you experience
when trying to communicate amongst uh
sort of this like chaos of information
can um
be interesting or can can teach us
something about
governance
um yeah next slide
[Music]
please so um actually I'm going to just
go back to the other side really quick
because there's something I wanted to
add on to what Gober just saying there
Janita um something that's also kind of
interesting about uh
you know
modeling kind of uh communication system
based around Community rule is that the
the the kind of implementation of the
different kinds of culture modules um
can vary quite a bit so if you look at
this uh actually well you can't see it
because it's not on culture right now in
the GIF but in culture there's a values
module and we'll talk about that a
little more but one of the interesting
things is that that's a quite Broad
category for uh like structuring
communication uh as like mediated and
filtered through a language model um so
some of the modules are very uh like
narrowly defined and some of them are
more uh abstract um another thing that's
sort of interesting is the this tool was
kind of originally designed to basically
help
communities like Define the way that
their governance actually is uh rather
than necessarily the way that they want
it to be um it's more of a retrospective
Tool uh rather than a prospective tool
and part of the reason that is that it's
like that is because the community rule
itself is not actually programmatic in
the sense that um like setting up these
structures doesn't do anything um it's
not connected to any apis or um the web
app doesn't even do anything um other
than just represent and so kind of
thinking through how to translate this
into a um something that's programmatic
um was actually a really interesting
exercise and it's it's it's worth saying
that too because one of the things that
kind of was also part of the the impetus
for this work was some of the past uh
user research that we had done um with
communities who were interested in uh
incorporating more governance tooling
into their Suite of online tools um we
uh Valen I in particular did a lot of uh
user research um with Community uh
participants and leaders uh while we
were doing some uh work on both medo's
Gateway project and also um policy kit
and now Collective voice projects and
one of the things that came up a lot in
those conversations was the need for um
some kind of uh primer or some kind of
uh like accessible uh way to even
develop the kind of uh governance
muscles or impulses that an online
community would need to um really make
use of the the the tools and Community
rule is actually at least in my opinion
a really great tool for introducing
communities to um what like a very like
uh simple kind of representation for
what governance uh could look like the
drag and drop uh web app and the kind of
um Simplicity of like seeing your
structure represented even even though
like you can actually get these very
strange kinds of um
uh like recursive uh structures like you
could have values inside of a board
inside of a uh values inside of a board
inside of values inside of a board just
kind of uh infinitely recursing um but
it's a really accessible and
approachable way of um actually seeing
what it means to have a structure to
make something that is often implicit
expl um we heard that there is a lot of
this need for making governance more
understandable and tangible um and so
that's part of the reason that we were
taking Community rule as a foundation um
and then we also heard that um there was
this desire to have something that is
more
explicitly uh interactive um a lot of
tooling can sometimes be set up a poll
um and then let it run and um you don't
really get any kind of interactive
feedback as a result of participating in
that process
um it can feel like a lot of online
interactions where you do something
maybe you see like a react number go up
or down um but largely speaking you do
something and you kind of don't even
know if what you did had any impact and
um
so this idea of kind of creating uh a
way of introducing people to online
governance through play seemed to be
something that was coming up in our
research
um Janita talked about this a little bit
this this sort of in terms of the kind
of conceptual development of the project
moving from a kind of General governance
Tool uh and even like a game to thinking
of it more as a kind of uh surface for
governance uh
experiences um and I think this is maybe
important to linger on just a little bit
because um
uh there's something about having a good
experience with governance um or a
meaningful experience with governance
that can really change your whole
relationship to why you would even care
about the topic um and so uh even though
like as we'll kind of get into our game
is uh or our kind of governance
experiences are kind of designed in some
ways to kind of uh be
uh induce confusion um they're also
designed to kind of uh stimulate the
imagination for what a kind of
governance could look like um and still
have some fun in the way in order
to take basically translate the
experience of playing into thinking
about
implementing uh these kinds of systems
in your communities um the other thing
is that for I mean one of the hard
things about
designing uh
governance uh scenarios games
environments Etc is determining what the
resources are that are actually being
governed at all um it's it's very nice
to kind of Imagine This Very abstract uh
governance uh scenario but if there are
no like Stakes uh in in terms of
resources then there's really it's not
entirely true but it's it's much harder
to kind of devise a governance
interaction space and so you know I
think we started and maybe we'll pick up
a little bit on this in some of the kind
of prompting discussion later on um but
we started with this idea of kind of uh
living in a kind of like post
communication collapse type environment
um where people for whatever reason
still needed to communicate over the
internet but the ability to do that had
degraded so much um that uh
communication itself um was this kind of
or Clarity of meaning was a scarce
resource of sorts um and the other thing
that we were interested in was thinking
about um how
to how to kind of like uh produce that
kind of scarcity uh or that kind of
fleeting sense of meaning um and the way
that we use culture modules was
uh one way of kind of artificially
placing people in these kind of abstract
uh communication environments so um yeah
I'll go to the next
slide uh Janita will talk a little bit
about the D20 aora
mode yeah so um what you see going on
here on on the right is um the D20
aora so the game is is basically broken
up into two modes there's the
Agora um or sorry the bot rather um is
broken up in two modes the Agora is what
we're looking at it's kind of this um
asynchronous environment where all of
the um you know culture decision Etc
modules are available to experiment with
but there's no kind of active game or
narrative going on that requires um
people's synchronous
attention um so um we we yeah we
intended the Agora to be um an
experimentation Zone and the jump off
point for the um the actual games
experiences whatever you want to call
them um and and we'll talk about that
second piece in a
bit
this is um basically just a kind of uh
GIF but actually because we're doing the
stream this way it's basically redundant
so just going to the next
slide um so we're going to go into a
little bit more detail about uh the way
the culture modules uh are implemented
and uh uh designed
um we'll start with hazel and then I'll
pick up a little bit
after yeah um I think culture module is
one of the really interesting
functionalities that we build and it's
um the way through which we mediate kind
of all messages and communication
through the switching on and off of
culture modules so to give an
introduction um I think culture modul is
one of our most notable features um and
it works to influence the group's
communication Norms with what we call um
we we picked up the term culture modules
from the community rule um where
basically we use um large language
models to modify the content and the
input of users messages and temporarily
place the users in the artificially
constructed uh culture communication
environment and a lot of these culture
modules have pre-generated large
languish model prompts um that the AI
use to transform the text input um of
the user's message on Discord and give
an output and we see a lot of the
Transformations happening here if you
type something the you will be your
language be mediated and changed by a
bot and um with reference to like
whatever culture model that culture
module that's active um so these are the
six culture modules that we've built so
far um and to just yeah we have amplify
we have eloquence obscurity ritual value
wild card um amplify just intensifies
the message sentiment like if I say that
you know today is fine um it's going to
amplify it to be something like today is
great or today's awesome um The Best Day
Ever um eloquence makes messages more um
persuasive and in our uh formulation it
kind of turns the message into like a
Shakespearean like poetry kind of way
which is really really interesting to
read out loud um in the environment M
and obscurity kind of makes the messages
more obscure by like a scrambling of
words but we actually found out like
really surprisingly that it's still kind
of readable if you stare at it for a
little while but it just makes it a
little bit harder to read um and ritual
is interesting because it actually
changes the meaning of your input it
will align if you we turn on the ritual
module um it will like align your
message and to like with the previous
message that's being sent um that if the
pr person say like you know I love like
tea or something and you say I hate tea
it would change it to like I like tea to
have this like really interesting
mediated uh group consensus that's very
constructed um and we have values we
have a list of values is defined in the
oror channel you can propose revision to
it and you can check values with the
check values um function um and the last
one is a little bit special the Wild
Card module um it transforms messages
into the voice um of the culture that's
being defined by the previous group um
so this is um like a special one we
built in um it's designed to construct
like a new culture module every time a
group successfully completes a build a
community Quest so uh the transformation
prompt is constructed using the text
content of the decisions made um through
governance mechanisms uh made during the
quest and made by the group and the
questions the players are tasked with
making a decision are related to the
voice that's going to uh formulate and
inform the what the wild wild card um
culture module is and we will talk a
little bit more about the build
community quests later and I'll pass to
send to talk a little bit about the um
conceptual thinking behind using um AI
generated
prompts yeah um
I we T I talked about it actually a
little bit already um kind of maybe
before it was scheduled in our
presentation but I think one thing that
um maybe to kind of uh come at it from a
different perspective is
um you know we had people at um dweb
Camp uh when we did an in-person play
test of this and they um when when the
eloquence mode was turned on they ended
up just like reading these posts out
loud um and afterwards we had people
sort of talking about how there was this
they could imagine a scenario where um
they're in a Discord or some kind of
communication platform and people are
basically talking past each other um
they're on their own individual tracks
and there's the the idea of kind of
coordinating or responding to what the
other person was saying is basically uh
impossible um and they said it would be
interesting if they had the ability to
go into a kind of eloquence mode um or
step into a channel um where all the
communication was structured in this way
and I think this kind of points to the
something that I think we want to come
back to in the the discussion but this
kind of um question of producing
artificial uh stability in the
environment um and um like I think often
[Music]
it's maybe speaking for myself I think
often when I'm posting um I become very
attached to what it is that I'm posting
um for a couple reasons the the content
is um like I can really only express
myself through text usually um and so a
lot of the uh nuances uh of course of
how I might actually Express something
are lost in the communication platform
or the
medium um but also there's the kind of
sense that like what I'm saying is also
kind of part of a long uh archival
history uh and part of the kind of
reputation that I've uh either
explicitly or implicitly developed
within a
community whoa the chat um and uh
um being able to kind of create a a
situation where everyone who's posting
is kind of conditioned by the same logic
of communication I think uh helps to
serve a coordinating function um even if
it's a frustrating coordinating function
um but it also serves to give a little
bit of distance between what it is that
you're saying and what it is that you're
communicating and then how you continue
to communicate as a result of those
Transformations um people including
myself also noticed that the way that
you type changes because you're in some
ways trying to kind of imagine how will
your text be transformed um by the
language model and I think this kind of
introduction of a kind of flexibility um
in this kind of artificially stable
system um ows for a slightly different
approach to thinking about how you make
decisions with other people online um I
think it it increases the kind of uh
complexity uh of making decisions
because the ability to accurately
communicate is is made more challenging
but it opens you up to um new ways of
relating to your peers in that
environment um and so I think one thing
that we're sort of interested in is um
how do these culture modules kind of
influence uh the decision- making uh
patterns within online
communities so at this point we were
planning on doing a demo um but the the
Discord is already quite uh active and
the culture modules have been uh pretty
thoroughly engaged with um but one thing
that we were interested in is sort
of right now the Discord uh bot and the
project is hosted on uh our Discord
server um we still need to go through
the process of setting it up as uh a bot
that other uh Discord servers can
install if there's interest the code is
open source and uh you can set the
environment variables and actually just
uh put it in your own Discord the reason
that we're I'm saying this is because
like right now it's hosted here and this
is a kind of decontextualized space on
the internet in some ways um like people
from your community are here right now
and you're missing all of the context of
the channels um the the kind of flare
that you might have set up with your
account um the ability to interface with
the kind of specific environment that
you uh operate in um and we're actually
really curious to see what that is like
because right now it feels kind of
distanced and also there's no real
incentive or magnetism to this
particular Discord server um the only
reason you would come here is to like
play with this but it's not integrated
into the place where you are in
community with others and so to kind of
stimulate or sorry stimulate that
experience a little bit we thought it
would be interesting to have maybe
alongside the rest of the presentation
um people having a conversation about
something to do with active inference um
we were thinking that it would be
interesting to have just a kind of
General um account from the active
inference community of what it is that
they're interested in with active
inference
um and um how they understand the term
and then um to maybe kind of just carry
on uh attempting to have a conversation
in the way that you might normally do it
in your own Discord um just to kind of
give a little bit of that sense of the
the kind of Transformations happening in
a contextually meaningful
environment so um I'm not going to pause
on this we'll just go to the the next
slide uh and this is going to be uh
Janita talking about uh one of the
specific culture modules which is
values um so did you intend for there to
be um a few moments for
discussion uh uh for discussion like in
the in the
Discord yeah
um I was thinking I'll read a question
from the chat and also we can talk a
little bit about active inference or
continue on but I'll read a question
first upcycle Club writes can you
combine two or more modules into a new
fused
one yeah um I think that's actually what
we were experiencing a few minutes ago
um so you can have any number of culture
mod modules running at the same time um
right now I think there aren't any
culture modules running but if for
example we wanted to turn on
amplify as well as
um
eloquence um anything anyone P going to
be run through both of these prompts so
um your the sentiment of your message
will both be Amplified and transformed
into Shakespeare
English
um one of the interesting things to
point out from like a technical
perspective in terms of how the code is
actually implemented is there the order
in which the culture modules are
activated has an impact on the way that
the text is transformed um it's the
culture models are stored in a list and
that list is being read through in order
um and the Order of the list determines
the the way like the the sequence of the
processing so you have your input text
let's say we have amplifi then eloquence
so your text goes to the amplify
transformation and then the output of
that goes to the eloquence
transformation um so there's there's
even kind of an ability to
create uh like basically Amplified
followed by eloquence and eloquence
followed by amplify are two kind of
different functions it and I mean that's
like in a technical sense but there's
another way in
which in my experience anyways the the
eloquence module kind of has this way of
overriding more or less all the other
modules um it's so distinctive in terms
of the way that it's uh character cized
um that I often find that if I want to
get a sense of the flavor for the other
modules I have to deactivate the
eloquence module um there's also um you
know uh I can't remember but I think in
the um the Agora you're not
even the the ways of changing the
culture modules isn't exposed or maybe
it's not exposed in the quests but to to
answer to also kind of answer what I
think the person in the chat might have
been asking is there's no way to kind of
make like to specify a module um that
isn't already specified um so you're
kind of you kind of have what you're
given the Wild Card module changes um as
a result of the quest um and um it's
only temporary so um after another group
plays the quest then the Wild Card
module changes um we would like to
explore the idea of more or less being
able to kind of specify the way in which
um the large language model is
transforming the text um but that uh
that I think there's a lot of uh ways
that the the kind of uh system was
architected it was very kind of organic
and not uh predetermined maybe at some
point J need to be interested in talking
about that but um the way that it was
developed didn't kind of have the path
dependencies that led us to uh a system
where you could um just create your own
module on the
flag awesome and just one more question
from Pablo FM he wrote If in our role
playing game we have our set of values
and our lingo and lore can it be
adapted uh so one thing that we we uh I
kind of mocked up a a um a very simple
like web app um that would allow people
to kind of basically Define their own
quests um and it it never really was
finished being developed but we're
interested in definitely being able to
let people construct their own role
playing scenarios Define their values in
advance um maybe even have them stored
in a database every time that the the
server where the bot is hosted is
restarted um the all of the data is
wiped because it's just stored to of the
way that governance is conducted in that
community so you can imagine joining a
Discord server and then um in order to
participate in some collection of
channels um you first need to go through
a governance Quest um and part of that
would involve communities being able to
Define their governance um in advance
and the way that their Quest is
structured so that when people join they
have a stable reproducible
experience um and this is also the the
the idea of kind of working with
Community rule we we explored this idea
of like actually
exporting the um the when you play a
quest you have these different
opportunities to change which culture
module you're interfacing with um what
decision-making method you're uh module
you're using and we had this idea of
kind of showing people how they how
their governance uh stack or their
governance structure changed over time
and then allowed them to basically
export the any thce of that and then use
it as a way of uh generating a new Quest
so these are all like kind of future
development ideas um but the short
answer to Pa's question is
no awesome continue on this is really
fun really fun definitely bringing a
smile to many people and there's a lot
of a lot of seeds that you planted like
the
contextless the decontextualized or the
recontextualizing of the dialogue in a
space that's new to us it's in your
lobby and there's all these different
formal informal structures so we'll
return to some of this but let's see a
little
more awesome
cool uh okay yes so Janita to talk about
values yeah so
um so another one of the culture modules
we have available is called the values
module um so I think Hazel or ENT have
touched on this earlier in the
presentation it's basically um a way
that you can sort of um softly enforce
the values of uh your community so um
anyone can um propose uh so there's kind
of a fixed number of values that we have
and anyone can propose a revision uh to
um any one of these values to replace it
with a new value um and then what you
can do is when someone posts a message
um you can see if that message is in
alignment with the values that the the
community have chosen by running this
command called check values so um I'll
just demonstrate that
on um on a message so we see at
the um I think someone ran the the
values command
so uh the community defined values we
have are inclusivity collaboration Trust
no respect and
intentionality um so I'm going to go
ahead and
run check values on upcycle club's
message um and the values analysis
appears to be that this message does
indeed align with our values and then
there's a description for for why the
bot thinks that it aligns with the
values
um uh yeah so so
um just another yeah building block that
we've included um
to to sort of allow people to experiment
with like how how things can be made
more um things that are generally um
implicit can be made more
explicit
um and
uh okay yeah I guess we can
try if Daniel if you want to try the
proposed value
revision just propose
uncore value underscore revision and
then it'll take you through the flow of
um replacing the no respect
value maybe go go through it on your
side just because that's what screen's
captured but this is
epic it's very flexible and I'll just
read one comment just while you're
setting it up I'll read one comment from
Dave he wrote here's a very practical
application of the kind of
Transformations you're demoing please
consider working on this at some point
glossing a discourse that's expressed in
one vocabulary into a discourse
expressed in a different analogous
vocabulary identifying corresponding
terms and Concepts in two fields or in
two approaches to a given field is
expensive deploying the result of such
Discovery will be useful on its own and
a Spur to the effort to develop more
correspondences this would involve a lot
of under the hood activity required by
full machine translation EG German to
French but could be driven by much
simpler rules AKA
patterns thank you
Dave all right so you're typing up
respect and justifying
it yeah so so you'll see that um we all
have the the option to object it's kind
of like um a pass by default unless
there are any objections to the values
within a certain time period um so
provided that no one yeah lazy consensus
is the term for that uh decision- making
process um provided that no one objects
to this value it'll be it'll be added to
our
list cool how long is the time like you
could set different amounts of
time yeah I think the default is like a
minute minute yeah yeah you could set
the time like you could program that but
uh we haven't partially because
one the someone could set it for like 60
Minutes um or someone could set it for
like one second I mean you could like
specify the like the boundedness of
what's allowed um but usually
because anyone who objects to one of
these values is going to be able to
pretty quickly realize they object um
our sense was that you really don't need
that much
time for this
decision yeah oh to totally makes sense
it just reflects how that could be a one
month review process like in a dii
scientific review setting with the right
interfaces or it could be really rapid
like feedback from the individuals and
they're time bound activity and then
that feeds back into the game like new
rule here's how we propose new rules or
here are the options for rules or here's
how we're going to apply which
filter and that just adds so many plot
twists even before active inference or
without any kind of cognitive modeling
at all or systems modeling just
approaching it from the pure game play
it's really fun and people in which are
like yeah already pointing out a lot of
ways it can be used to play if not be
more
useful yeah one thing to point out
that's kind of hidden at the moment uh
is so let's go to this value analysis of
upcycle Club um uh where are they so
they
were um aligned and if we go to their
uh
profile um oh okay no
um there should be something that
uh I saw that there was a melline tag on
Friendly's
profile uh yeah yeah the I don't know if
it's doing it right now but um I think
we might have taken it out at some point
because it wasn't part of the the full
feature set that we wanted to ship but
um this function can assign an aligned
or misaligned uh tag based on the result
of the the analysis and then you could
do do whatever you want with that um
from a programmatic perspective one idea
would be that like if uh you as a
community are aligned um any user that
you're aligned with um you are
either not affected by the disruptions
in language that are caused by the
culture modules um or the effects are
less intense and so there's an incentive
to uh remain aligned if you want to be
able to effectively coordinate with your
peers so
um the the demo thing the demo idea that
we were going to um explore was
um asking uh people in the chat to
answer the question of what do you value
in communication environments um perhaps
from the perspective of active inference
and then we can do some uh value uh
analysis um you even propose new values
um and we can sort of to see this kind
of uh iterative feedback loop play
out um so maybe we'll just leave that
again like just keep playing with that
in the background in the chat um feels
uh you know something about just
stopping and watching a chat and not
saying anything
feels uh
too strange um so um uh yeah we'll go to
the um building a community mode um I
know that I'm supposed to talk about
this but I feel like I've been talking
for a really long time even though we
like structured the speaking setup um
hazel do you want to talk about this at
all or do you want me to still pick it
up go for it okay um yeah so uh building
Community uh we have a build a community
Quest um it's uh we actually explored a
bunch of different quests this kind of
like post communication collapse quest
uh we explored one that might still be
in the repa somewhere called the Josh
game um which was a uh kind of uh
actually hezel do you can you talk about
that just very briefly like what the
Josh game was yeah um I think the Josh
game is like um it's like intending to
be an um a game that's placed on
individual identity it's kind of
inspired by I think one of us saw like a
news online about the like IRL Josh game
that a bunch of people are named Josh um
and they kind of had like a just like a
fake like noodle sword fight um for the
name Josh where the last person standing
who like won like via Rock Paper Caesars
is the last person who's crowned Josh um
and the rest of the people like lost
their ability or lost their right to be
Josh um and I think like through we kind
of made some version of that where we
all enter the game with our like Avatar
and name replaced with like a random
Josh it can be like josling Josh or like
Josh or tree Josh or whatever else um
and and then we kind of like compete we
kind of give SPI some um speech in this
like
kind of word based contest where we kind
of compete to be who's the most worthy
Josh or who's the last Josh um and yeah
it's just like um like a playful way to
experiment with who's who um how do you
like what's in the name and how do you
like kind of like establish or spin out
like a little playful identity and we
imagine like a lot of different ways we
can potentially play with that um but
but that's the that's the general that's
the general like um playful context of
the Josh game cool thank you hesel uh
another funny uh thing about that game
is um uh Joshua tan um uh was the
executive director of medov at that time
and uh is still currently at medov as a
research director um and uh we actually
never played this with him but it's uh
his uh GitHub handle is the last Josh um
and so I don't know there's something
very funny about spending one's time uh
making a game that like is not even
directly referencing someone but is yet
nevertheless connected somehow like
organizationally so a little bit of you
know meta for for the the stream
posterity um so to to the build a
community quest uh yeah 25 minute
narrative bu game um and um you can
prompt it in the chat um I mean you can
try it uh it's been a little while since
we've actually done it um the thought
might break um so and also it takes a
long time to do but um basically um you
can set up the parameters of a quest um
you can decide how many players need to
join um and whether or not are generated
as part of the the quest and then you go
and you play it and the goal in the in
the game or the quest is to basically
kind of as a group collectively
establish um yourself as a new group to
give yourself an identity of some sorts
um you you have to answer questions like
what's your name uh what's the main
topic of interest that your group talks
about and in what way does your group
can speak or communicate to each other
and for each of these questions there
are proposal functions um you can WR
various proposals um there are voting uh
decision-mak processes there are some
deliberation questions that are sent um
and there are also different methods for
making decision um at the moment I think
we've implemented
uh two or three like a very small amount
of decision-making methods um and then
there's a a Fourth Kind of implicit
feudalism uh method um which is if the
Google players um are unable to make a
decision after three tries the bot
basically just picks a decision at
random um partially
because um I don't know it's it's hard
to know like how deep we want want to go
into the implicit feudalism thing um but
basically one kind of like background
thing that's also connected with all
this is the idea of um thinking about
the ways in which the platforms were
used to communicate with each other are
uh structured and Nathan schneer is
written a really nice piece called um
the implicit feudalism of uh social
media and and it is looking at like the
history of the server architecture the
server client architecture um from as
far back as the BBS era up to now and
his argument which I won't go into a lot
of detail about is basically this
architecture and the ways that we
communicate in general are
basically uh representative of a kind of
uh feudalism um it's not explicit but
it's just implicit in the way that we
communicate and
um one of the thesises is that we could
give communities online a uh different
ways of um governing or setting up
governance systems that are not
inherently feudalistic and this is kind
of where the modular governance and the
the metag governance angle of this
project comes into play um and a lot of
the the game is about kind of
introducing uh people to the idea that
they could change
uh on the Fly how they make decisions um
they can have agency over um the way um
their communication happens in a way
that is not uh is circumscribed by the
developers of platforms and to be honest
it's also circumscribed by us um it's
it's very difficult to create a system
that doesn't have any kind of
predetermined uh structures in place um
but for example in the game if if you
fail to make a decision about any of
these topics then you're given the
ability to uh change the way you make
decisions um and then if none of that
works then a decision is just made for
you and this is in some ways meant to
kind of bring to the surface for players
the ways in which um they can and cannot
exercise
agency um when communicating and
the other thing to say about this this
question why you go through this process
is that um all of the answers to these
questions are then uh fed into a
template for an llm transformation
module this is the Wild Card module and
what that means is that like one thing
that I think is there there are a lot of
experiments with kind of uh multi-user
input uh interfaces into
llms but not so many um and I think one
thing that's sort of interesting to
think about is how can we open up um an
imaginary about um I guess two things
one is um having more uh Collective uh
inputs
into um the the kind of uh
way that the large language model is
interfacing with uh our Communications
um but also kind of um being clear
through experience the ways in which the
way that we communicate and the
decisions that we make have an impact on
the ways in which our environments uh
change around us um so this is kind of
maybe like the stigma kind of thing a
little bit like you have these like uh
interactions these like uh uh uh
pheromones that people are leaving
behind which are their decisions and
then you kind of experience the result
of that in the Agora and that also
changes the way that you interact in the
Agora and maybe the way that you
interact in the build a community
Quest um so I mentioned that if a
failure if a decision fails um then you
have the ability to uh change it and the
way that that happens is through a kind
of continuous input mechanism um the
there's a kind of multi-user uh
input
uh uh there's a way of uh inputting your
uh preferences for a decision um and
then once um a certain level of
preference collectively has been
expressed then uh a decision is made and
the mechanism is triggered um it's also
a display of community conviction and uh
it also just kind of acknowledges the
fact that there are governments failures
I think one thing that kind of comes up
sometimes in discourses around
governance and also perceptions around
governance is that governance is kind of
a when we talk about it as a system um
it can sometimes uh or a model it
sometimes be perceived as this like
static set and fix and don't think about
again uh experience and sort of a lot of
the literature that kind of thinks about
especially the emergence of meta
governance in in governance in general
as a kind of development of
government um is basically like
hyperfocused on the ways in which
failures manifest in in decision-making
um so we want wanted to make sure that
when this happened um there was a way of
exercising agency and and kind of giving
players the experience of steering or uh
responding to the the
environment uh another thing to maybe
say just quickly about this is that this
kind of uh mechanism is also one of the
like most uh popular uh often cited uh
kind of
uh ways of uh references for this is
Twitch Plays Pokemon um which is
basically
a emulator of Pokemon uh uh setup on
Twitch and then some python binding so
that anytime someone types uh up in the
chat then uh an up uh command is uh sent
to the emulator and the character moves
up um and so you you could have a chat
that's basically just collectively
distributedly controlling the game and
uh this is cool and extremely chaotic um
but there are maybe like two scenarios
in Twitch place Pokemon or like in
Pokemon where you really have to press
the same button maybe like six times in
a row in order to even move to the next
part of the map um and
so you can't stay in the kind of pure
chaos mode um or else you'll never
complete the game and so the developer
of the the python binding uh set up this
way for people to oscillate or move
between uh what was it like uh democracy
and Anarchy um and and when you're in uh
Anarchy mode it's exactly like we just
described it's all continuous just
taking the input um and then when you're
in democracy mode there's a kind of time
buffer in which um all the responses are
collected and whichever response gets
the most input in that period of time is
the response that's triggered so it sort
of slows down
the the reading of input um and allows
for groups to coordinate and actually
get past these situ situations uh where
they couldn't otherwise and then it's
super interesting project it's very old
at this point as well but it's I highly
Rec who are not familiar with it already
to go to look at it um another great
reference in this area is uh trust uh
moving castles project which is also
looking at Community controlled games
through twitch and is uh kind of a more
contemporary example um
yeah so we wanted to demo this and you
can see that it's already happening in
the Discord chat a little bit um people
are typing a culture module and then
plus or minus one and then once it
passes a certain threshold then uh that
module is activated so we didn't have
any prompt for this one uh so maybe
we'll just kind of move to the next
section unless you know wants to pause
and discuss something since that seems
to be a pattern here demo
[Music]
discussion I think one quick thing I
would add is we told we we built the
cool down time because I think when we
are playing it we ourselves find ways to
break it and cheat on the system um I
think that's also part of the fun of
building the game of thinking about not
not just thinking about ways that we can
play but also to think about to play
through the disruption by disrupting the
disruption um which was really
interesting which is why we built the
cool down so nobody can spam and just
get what they want at least not
immediately yeah that's a great Point uh
yeah yeah thank you
um anything you want to add maybe Janita
or
okay
um
so progress
um we've done a playthrough of this at D
camp we talked about that a little bit
um we did a kind of annotated uh
playthrough uh like an anotated version
of that playthrough um I'm not going to
show it because it's not set up um and I
can't remember where the link is
actually
but anyways um that was a really
interesting process and we should make a
slide for that next time um we also did
a presentation as part of a symposium in
Geneva called uh the she Seashore of
endless worlds um and we've also
presented this at a uh one of the weekly
meta governance seminars so um and now
we're here um which is very exciting um
and I'm really looking forward to this
stream existing because I think this is
uh a very fun uh engagement with the
project um so yeah with that um with
that maybe we would move into a little
bit of discussion even though we've had
this nice kind of uh interjection
discussion so far um and we were
thinking of um like in what ways is this
kind of uh project um how does the
active inference Institute Community
kind of see relevance in it um I guess
in terms of both maybe setting up
experiments or um kind of using it as a
complement to or the subject of research
and then another thing that we're
interested in is kind of thinking about
this kind of this thing that we alluded
to earlier this kind of like uh
communication collapse in like a kind of
post llm or whatever uh kind of uh
technology were post at this point uh
communication environment where um
the like there's this idea as far as we
understand we're not experts in active
inference that like one of the kind of
reasons to study and model this um in
this field is to kind of be able
to uh anticipate and respond to
unpredictable environments somehow like
the idea of active inference and I'm
curious that this is corrected is to
kind of produce a kind of more stable
system than uh we might um otherwise uh
design and and
this game in many ways kind of purposely
introduces um uh instability into the
communication but it's also those those
those disruptions are themselves kind of
metastable environment ments and so
there's this kind of strange interplay
between stability and instability and
the ways in which this kind of experien
of of um expanding the kind of
governance imaginary for how we might
interface in a more
ambiguous uh uh epistemic uh context so
um we'd love to discuss that a little
bit and then to maybe um leave uh
everyone with some information about us
um here are our names and our respective
roles in the project um some of our
contact information um and then some
links to our projects and um we should
also mention that the project was
incubated and uh uh supported by the Met
governance project so yeah that's our
presentation thank you so much for
having us and um um I'll leave the
discussion prompts up and would love to
see where the conversation
goes awesome well thank you for
presenting
this
like there's a lot to say a lot of
places to jump in it feels so natural
despite the tech in some ways being so
new in
practice and in our hands but even
though you all have made this it feels
like people just slotted into it and I
think it it does touch on a lot of
active inference ideas like on a more
technical but also on a more informal
level like just starting with the
informal the idea that there's multiple
agents or multiple entities with varying
Blends new mixtures new filters and
overlays of bodied and digital all these
different modifications and and
layerings and identities so this kind of
like open
cyber complex identity engagement
space and the way that still there are
these features of ecological
psychology and that those fundamental
features like relating to sense making
on the inbound and decision selection on
the outbound we can understand whether
it's like leaving an emoji or the words
that are
produced all all of that is behavior and
it's behavior um that's different but
with our body so there's all these kind
of like Rich Dynamics so the field
provides more questions than answers on
those fronts but shows like how far the
Gap is between the general unified
approach and how deep the last um mile
is in application
but this really like connects it from
what otherwise could be super abstract
about like multi-agent online
interactions which is like what the
research papers in metov or in active
inference how they'll describe it and
this like really connects it and it's
like in this
Discord so it kind of becomes embodied
in the real chat so that was one thought
another thought was like
it it shows that words matter and that
our speech acts online
matter by representing them in this kind
of fun and unique way and there's other
ways to to represent people's speech
online like going back and curating
older posts that was something we had
done or seen in the metago
slack and then here with some new shiny
affordances from the language models and
all of
that um to have words that have informal
import with the sentiment that we convey
uh filtered or not and then also to
bring in Acts that have kind of Quasi
formal import like actually changing the
rules of a game at some level of
analysis and and being able to hold the
fun and
playful and comical and that whole
aspect and also seeing that that's even
paradoxically or not like what's
important for high reliability
distributed settings or for establishing
trust or new ways of communicating when
there's
change thank you for yeah thank you for
letting us speak I think to be fully
transparent I think we are still very
actively uh this is not a finished
project and we don't uh present it as a
finished project I think we're still
very much in the process of imagining um
use cases not just use cases but places
where Um this can be immediately useful
or playful or make sense right because I
think today we're really fortunate to
demonstrate it in a way that feels that
has the split screen it demonstrate in a
way that feels very calm but we've also
had like playthroughs and demonstrations
where when it needs to be like put into
like say like 10 minutes it's really
confusing it's just like a bunch of
messages blowing up and everybody
speaking um and I think yeah some users
think it's really kind of chaotic um
yeah I think um yeah I think like we
yeah we we really appreciate speaking
today but would really still love to
hear from you guys um what are some of
the use cases um and even like modules
that you find that's like most
accessible um or any research potential
that could potentially um like be
interesting stemming from this or other
ways that we can I think play together
like for the purpose of like governance
Spirit
spiritedness cool if someone writes
something in the chat we can read it but
just one thought that's kind of a
general approach in active inference
modeling which is analogous to some of
the work we did like in 2022 with dii
distributed science decentralized
science is take a look at systems that
are often engineered from the top
down and then think about it from the
bottom up in terms of the sensory inputs
and then the capacity for Action the
affordances of different agents in the
system and so take that kind of view
from the inside so one kind of
scaffolding
of an approach that is pretty General
cross active inference settings is
like connect up that constraint or like
the modifications that you're putting
onto the
environment and then interface that with
schemes
for the kinds of input that people
receive and actions that they receive so
like different actions maybe people have
different roles so they can only do
Emojis or people can type in chat and
then different inputs people could see
different channels or maybe some people
are seeing it visually and some people
are having it read so make a kind of
scheme for who are the players and then
with the players plus the
board on that's kind of the board
game setup and it's a different board
and different players but I think even
with the um title of the project you
kind of allude
to that role playay
um yeah that's really interesting um
yeah the title is also kind of uh a
funny one um because there are no dice
involved um uh but it's it's catchy um
the yeah I think having like more
persistent um
consequences uh is an interesting uh
Avenue I mean the kind of aligned
misaligned uh role tagging that that we
showed is kind of pointing a little bit
in that direction but um yeah like
imagining like uh kind of blank server
and then like the first thing you do is
interact with this and everything that
you learn about the server is a result
of the decisions and interactions that
you have um through this would
be like a really interesting way of kind
of producing a somewhat like
Labyrinth
nonstable uh constantly
evolving uh environment for people to
interact in um and like yeah that's a
great idea um it's really
interesting I mean that is newly on the
table and so it's exciting to think
about
um digital environments whether they're
personalized or shared that have a
defined construction to them so it's
legible here's how we're modifying the
incoming posts or something so there
could be situations where that's exposed
or like transparent or open source and
then there could be other situations
where for one reason or another they
don't and they would be accepting the
tradeoffs with or without sharing that
kind of
information and it it brings like new
um Nuance to all the filters that we do
receive information
through and as that becomes more
post or
multi-lingual then there's a there's so
many new ways that this
can come into play because people are
hashing these things out and they are
having a a model of who's aligned and
not and so making some of it
visible can
maybe that's a a disconcerting look in
the mirror so not
every representation is probably right
for every setting but in
like different settings there will be
people who love
this mod
facilitator meta
Governor
role and you're you're producing to TOS
that help bring that to the discords
where people really
are yeah uh there's there's two things
that are interesting somehow there one
is um I mean actually working with the
Discord uh interfac is and also the API
is actually kind of a nightmare um like
there's a there's a function that we
have that um does a bunch of like text
streaming so it's taking a message and
then like sending a couple words chunks
at a time to kind of produce this effect
that the the message is being written by
some external agent um but there's a
pretty aggressive rate limit on how
quickly you can edit messages um in
Discord um so there are some kind of
like constraints there um and I think
the there's
um there's something about this um I
think I can one thing that I can sort
of see is that
there this this kind of model that we're
talking about of like a kind of really
uh emergent and flexible and somewhat
kind of
unpredictable uh structure for and and
and a structure where no one person
really has the same view on the system
there's no uh holistic view um maybe
even as an admin um then like you're
opening up so many kind of unpredictable
moderation questions I mean we already
have enough
challenges um or at least the discourse
will will kind of point to the the kind
of numerous moderation challenges that
we have uh and kind of
maintaining uh our dis our discursive
spaces aligned with some kind of sense
of community value um but like the
ability to kind of have uh an
environment where no one has the same
View kind of opens up this like huge
like how do you even conceive of
moderation in that way um there's
there's also the like a there's also
this um this problem of information
overload um so we explored like having
the the the Genera response um actually
show you the information um like the the
original input using like a spoiler tag
um but it it was just too just too much
like it was visually cluttered um and
another thing that actually happens here
is like I want to figure out how to like
have it match token length so that the
input and the output are kind of like
correlated to each other and length
right now there's this kind
of uh it it will elaborate so much that
it breaks the natural flow of
communication um and like it introduces
a kind of temporal friction and so like
more
moderation uh to kind of expose what's
happening in the background kind of
naturally puts a kind of like break in
some way on the kind of way in which
we're communicating which could you know
be beneficial or uh or not thing and
then yeah like this like dystopian thing
yeah I mean there are a lot of ways that
this could be applied that are
uh not benevolent um I very like
authoritarian um in in nature so it's uh
it is there is also this kind of yeah I
think the yeah the moderation surface
just
become
so difficult to figure out how you
actually
approach yeah what one
interesting approach there is that now
with these
llms the space of moderation is in the
semantic not just the syntactic so a lot
of Discord Bots or trending lists or all
these things are based upon the syntax
of like how something is spelled or
actually like how word is used with all
the kind of false positives and false
negatives now we're in a different space
or mode of false positives and false
negatives with the
semantics and that's a a different and a
more latent space and one that really
gets at the cognitive diversity and
different people's understanding of
different words and decisions and events
but that's kind of the real space
as well and so making the maps of that
cognitive semantic territory instead of
saying okay no name calling here's the
list of names now that is going to
be elaborated on from something and and
maybe uh and also just
so new Vistas for how people want to
communicate and
engage or not and like you brought up
massive opportunities and challenges for
attention and
overload and just the pace of all this
augmented text is extremely
high and so it's very
intense also though people do a lot of
intense digital
experiences yeah it's so true I think
there's like a some relationship between
the intensity of digital experience that
you're
uh comfortable or have previously
experienced and how quickly you pick up
this this spot um we've done this in
some other contexts where people are
just like I have no idea what is
happening um and I think if you are if
you tend to be like extremely online um
this feels very natural um and if you're
not it's it's
somehow just way it it's uh it's too
much um so that's also it's also
interesting from a governance
perspective as well it's like I mean I
can't make any real extrapolations but I
wonder if in terms of the kind of VI the
viability of online community-based
self-governance if there's a kind of
correlation between the kind of like
intensity
uh digital experiences that that the
community is uh game for and how broadly
effective they will be or adaptive to
online governance they will be um
whereas communities that are less active
or less digitally intense um would
generally find online community
self-governance um harder to
adopt that's super interesting investing
and communities that have variation
amongst their participants in that as
well
well this is an
epic part one and kind
of play through I guess with this like
maybe as we kind of close where do you
want to go from here or what would be
something cool in
2024 to get to or
try um I don't know maybe we can each
kind of try to give an answer to this um
uh I think one thing that would be
really cool is
like they cleaning up the code base um
so that it's like easier for other
developers to to actually extend the
work that we've been doing and
contribute meaningfully um I and also
getting this set up so that communities
can actually experience it in their own
uh contexts rather than just in the
server so if there's anyone uh who is
part of this community or who's watching
who's interested in um kind of sifting
through the codebase and figuring out
how to contribute um that would be
really cool
um yeah I think that's that's kind of my
thought I don't know Hazel Janita
anything from you
yeah I I'm on a similar page um I really
think of this spot and this tool right
now is like just a set of building
blocks that um communities can ideally
use to like configure their own
experiences and so um I think
um yeah I think it would be great to
figure out ways to extend this to make
it more accessible for for people to
continue to experiment and and build
upon what we've
done yeah I feel like I really wish that
more people watching this live stream or
not will just come talk to us and say hi
and tell us how we can make this more
useful or practical for you and that
would make us really happy and I think
another thing that um a topic that I'm
really interested in is what kind of
thing is Randomness in governance um how
does like being random work and having a
function that assigns like a random
value work um I think there there are
quite a bit of we build like a kind of
random Overlord function um in build a
in build a community Quest um but I feel
like that's something I really want to
explore more especially with regard to
um what's the relationship between um
Randomness and agency right like what's
the setup that that gives user like the
agency the feeling of agency of
governance um that's something I'm
interested in thinking through more um
and hopefully with this
project cool super exciting I hope
people in The Institute Discord and
elsewhere tune in to this kind of cool
way to think about our shared services
as governance Services really converting
a space
and taking everyone on this journey
that's
so in the moment that it's kind of like
intense and flies right by so it's been
an epic stream and maybe we can play
around with it as you all continue to
develop the framework so thank you
all till next time yeah thank you so
much for having
us cool
bye